My name is Joe and I live in a van. This
is my home. I've called this home for
about three and a half years. Name is El
Suave. It is a 1999 Dodge Ybody Explore.
I like the Y rear ends. It's a DY in the
back. Very rare vehicle. I've never seen
another one on the road. Alex did
capture one one time. Completely
off-rid. I'll show you the inside. I'll
show you the solar system. I'll show you
how I live. Come on in. It is pretty
cold, so I have my gas heater running
right here. All right, we have two beds
right here. I have a table that clips in
right there. I set this I have the
cooler to work on. I keep glow rods
inside my thing cuz I need them a lot.
But you can take your table and clip it
right here.
Y'all can both eat in your bed or you
can spin it to get by. That's why I cut
off the edges instead of rounding it.
The cooler works as a double bed. Uh we
found that out when Alex came here the
first time. It's the exact height. I
bought this at Walmart in Augusta
randomly, but I convert this to a double
bed and then we use this for storage. Uh
we have it set up for two right now.
That way you and your guy friends can
van around. No homo, one on each side.
Living in a van is all about just
finding your vibe. As you can tell, I
have antique sheets. I grew up sleeping
on these same sheets. that my mom is
from the 1950s.
That's my grandpa Marvin Pierman's wool
jacket. He's had that since like 1920.
And everything in here is is old and
reused and withtood the test of time.
Maple doors and little closet right
here.
So, this is my clothes. You know, you
don't need a whole lot in a van. The
whole purpose is to chase 70°.
Little drawers right here. Everything in
here is very small and intentional. This
is my coffee pot. I got it in Costa
Rica. This actually tastes better the
more you use it. And so you don't need a
whole lot.
Completely off grid water. We have
power. Uh obviously I'm not plugged into
anything. Fridge with freezer. Now this
is a fantastic thing because you can
have cold beer all across America.
I have a shower toilet combo. Look. So,
you don't need a whole lot of space to
shower.
You take that and you cut this down to
where it fits right above that. And then
you take one of these extra things right
here and you just clip it on there. So,
when you take a shower, it hits that and
it rolls right in. You know, the goal is
never to really or shower in your
van ever for any reason. I've spent
multiple summers out there without
or showering inside for an
entire 4 months. You dig a hole in the
ground and you in the woods like
every other animal on planet Earth. You
hop in an ice cold river. Dude, it's the
best way to live. You start hopping in
rivers and in the dirt, you'll
never go back to a bathroom again. But I
have it. Sometimes you're in a city and
you really don't have these things. And
it is illegal to piss in a Walmart
parking lot, but it is not illegal to
piss in an empty beer can in your van
and dump it in a Walmart parking lot.
They have conveniently placed little
green areas all around.
So, you know, van life is all about
freedom and not getting arrested. Got my
little table right here, which clips in
and out, which is really nice. You have
different seats and all these swivel
around, too. You can take them and
swivel them like that and turn both of
these around. Have a pretty good little
setup. I have color changing LED mood
lights in here. I can change the color
on. I have red in there. Not red and
blue. That's a bad combination. Keep it
there to ward off the bad spirits, you
know. And I have all the little things I
love. My Costa Rican water bottle. I
call this a goal. Talk about not wasting
anything.
That was full. It's a gut hoof. I have
Native American art from my neighbor
Gary in Washington. You know, different
things I've been to. Look, imported
these from India. These are brass cobra
handles that double as towel racks cuz
everything in a van has to have two or
more functions. You know, nothing does
just one thing. We use the bathroom for
storage a whole lot because, you know,
there's not a lot of place to put stuff.
Deceptively large storage spaces. I get
in my van and go. I always have enough
food. I have pasta. I have sardines. I
have tuna. I have beans. I have rice.
Everything I need to live. GoPro kit for
easy recording on the go. I have a
multiple camel backs cuz I'm an avid
trail runner. Fishing poles. Which is
easier, grocery store or river? Yeah,
man. Your job when you're in a van is
catch one trout. That's all you have to
do. There's water in the river to drink.
You don't have to filter it. Drink right
out of a glacial melt river and catch a
fish. Pick some blackberries. That's all
you have to do. White man stupid. He
invent job. Should have listened to the
red man. Let me show you the coolest
part of this is the solar setup. And
I'll tell you
a little bit of the electrical
engineering behind this. So right now
you can see we are using 2.4 amps taken
out. Right now we have a gas heater
running and this is all running off of
12 volt is lighting fridge freezer and
heater. Okay, so I'm going to cut on the
high voltage system. I have a 120 240
split phase inverter. Shout out to Big
Battery.
I only use Big Battery products, man.
Best company in America, probably the
world. So there you go. 12vt. And I'm
going to cut on the inverter.
Oh, you see it shot up. Now we're going
3.7.
Okay, that's cuz there's standby voltage
to run the 120. Now we have 120 coming
here. And you'll see me cut on. Let's do
the heater. The gas heater has heated it
up over 78° in here right now. Cut that
off. Now watch. Come over here to the
microwave. Ah, 45 amps going out right
now. And that's for the microwave. So,
we're using 12,200 watts an hour right
now to run a microwave and the the the
blower on the gas heater. Stop it.
And
whoa. Drop down to five.
Microwave is an energy intensive thing.
Everything else really doesn't pull much
energy. 4 amps. So, that's 100 watts to
run your water pump. So, it's going it's
running. It's just fan blowing right
now. There's not much going out. Gas
heater kicked off. You'll hear it when
the compressor starts running cuz right
now was just blowing it's just blowing
room temp air. But you know what's
funny? I never use the air conditioner
ever. I' I think I've cut it on like
twice. You know when we were sitting in
Florida working? You never really use
it. All right. Now look. You hear it?
Now you hear that compressor kick on.
Now watch. It's going up.
4.9. Now it's about to jump. Five 7.
See, now you can see the compressor just
started going
and you feel it's chilling. Now, it's
not working really hard to make AC cuz
it's freezing outside. The air it's
pulling is obviously pretty chilly, but
we're running the AC and it's only using
260 watts. We got a little bit coming in
from the solar, but then let's see.
Cut on pretty much everything.
Uh, so we got, you know, 57 amps going
out right now.
I don't really have much else to turn on
right now. I mean, you see the van's
putting out 60 amps consistently. I'm
running pretty much everything in here
all at the same time. That's how you
know the system is dialed in. I can run
anything simultaneously. I can try and
break this and it won't break. And
it's a real functional system. Do you
want to see what it looks like?
>> Cut it all off. And now you see
everything off. Now you see that two
amps. This is an important part.
Now, wow. Power going in. I cut the
inverter off. That's a 3 amp difference.
Amps time watts equal volts. We'll just
round that up to 27. 3 * 27. What is
that? 3 * 27. That's 81. All right. That
means 81 watts. That's how much energy
requires just to turn the inverter on in
most vans or in in most all RVs, this
van included. See this one right here?
Converter.
In most rigs, what they're doing is
taking DC energy out of the battery and
converting it to 120 volts of AC energy
to run to the panel. Then they're taking
a 120V to 12volt converter to drop it
back down to feed the lights and the
fridge. This fridge right here only
pulls 30 watts on average. That means
every hour it's only going to eat 30
watts. Just to turn the inverter on to
keep the fridge running takes 80 to 100
watts. It's literally takes three times
the energy just to turn the inverter on
to run the converter than it does to run
the fridge. Now you think about that.
That's little bits of energy. Yeah,
energy is like money. The devil is in
the details and money is made in the
margins. And I tried to live on a
5kwatth battery and it's not feasible.
Them people selling 5KW batteries,
they're they're selling you a lie. You
need at least 14 kW minimum to live in a
van. And so what I did was engineer this
differently. I have 12 volt. I have a
24volt battery. Why the hell couldn't I
get 12 volts out of that? Well, the
problem was the the ampacity and the
discharge, but I'll show you how I fixed
it. Cuz now you see all my 12 volts
still running, which is the majority of
what I use in here, the AC and the
microwave is very very very rarely. So,
I didn't need it a whole lot. So, that's
what I do. I'm running all this off a
battery because there's no energy loss.